January 21, 2017, became a special day
2017年1月21日は
for deaf people in Japan.
日本のろう者にとって
特別な日となりました
エホバの証人が日本手話版の
Jehovah’s Witnesses released
the book of Matthew
「マタイによる福音書」を
発表したのです
in Japanese Sign Language.
What, though, was behind these smiles?
これほどの笑顔があふれたのは
なぜでしょうか
When I used to read the Japanese Bible,
日本語の聖書は意味が
よく分かりませんでした
I really didn’t understand it,
仕方なく読んではいましたけど
so I forced myself to read—not much of a joy.
楽しくはなかったです
Right, it was hard to understand
and explain to people.
意味をつかんで人に説明
するのが難しかったね
分からない言語で聖書を読んでも
The Bible, written in a language
we do not know, will not move our heart.
それは心を動かしません
神のことを慕う気持ちを
培うという点では
Having no sign-language Bible
was a huge disadvantage
when it came to cultivating a longing for God.
手話という言語での聖書がないって
いうことはとても不利だったと思います
When making shepherding calls,
reasoning on a scripture
牧羊訪問でも この聖句を
ろう者の方と推論して
考えたいと思っても
with a deaf person was difficult if that scripture
その聖句がないので 難しさは
大きかったと思います
wasn’t translated into sign language.
There is a Bible in American Sign Language,
アメリカ手話版は出ていたので
うらやましく感じていました
so I was envious and wanted to see the Bible
ぜひ日本手話でも聖書を見たいと
待ち望んでいました
in Japanese Sign Language so much.
At last, approval was given for Bible translation
ついに 聖書の日本手話版の
翻訳が承認されました
into Japanese Sign Language.
翻訳チームの仕事の様子を見ていると
I noticed that the translation team
まず仕事を始める前に
祈りをささげています
offered a prayer
before they started each day’s work.
Also, when faced
with difficult translation problems,
翻訳で難しくなったときでも
エホバの聖霊に頼って
they relied on Jehovah’s holy spirit
through prayers
良い判断や決定がなされるようにと
祈って進めていたことは
本当に印象的でした
so that they could exercise good judgment.
It was impressive.
神の言葉がページから飛び出して
ろう者の心に達するために
There are various processes
needed for God’s Word
to jump off the page
and reach the heart of deaf people.
幾つもの過程を踏む必要があります
They considered carefully
how to express scriptures
ろう者が理解しやすい表現が
慎重に検討されます
so that deaf people would understand.
Let’s take an example:
“the lilies of the field” at Matthew 6:28.
マタイ 6:28の
「野のユリ」を例に考えてみましょう
I wasn’t able to understand
Matthew chapter 6 until now.
今までマタイ 6章をはっきり
理解できませんでした
I always thought,
‘“Birds of heaven” and “lilies of the field,”
「鳥」や「野のユリ」は
「王国を……第一にする」ことと
どんな関係があるんだろう？
と思っていました
What do they have to do
with “seeking first the Kingdom”?’
The translators individually read and research
翻訳者は各自 内容を
十分に理解できるまで
the source text
to fully understand what they’ll translate.
原文を読み 調査します
Then the team meets to discuss the text
次に チームミーティングで
アイデアを出し合って
and explore ideas
for translating certain concepts.
聖句の考えを手話に翻訳します
After the translation is complete,
手話翻訳が完成したら
the assigned brother signs the translation
to prepare the prompt video.
割り当てを受けた兄弟が
プロンプト･ビデオを準備します
Then studio recording takes place,
そのプロンプト･ビデオを見ながら
スタジオ収録を行います
referencing the prompt video.
The recorded movie is carefully edited
映像は丁寧に編集され
and prepared for delivery.
それから配信されます
In this case,
この例では 兄弟は花になりきり
the signer pretends to be a flower
機織り機で花びらを織ったり
and weaves his own petals
それを自分の顔に
縫い付けたりしています
and sews them on his face.
それからこう問いかけます
Then he asks,
“Flowers don’t do that, do they?”
「こんなことはしませんよね？」
God’s Word coming off the pages
ページを飛び出した神の言葉は
has reached the heart of deaf people.
ろう者の心に届きます
エホバが優しく教えて
くださっているのは
I understood for the first time
that Jehovah is kindly teaching us,
「王国を第一にするなら
必要なものは全て与えるから
‘If you seek the Kingdom first,
I’ll give you everything you need.
安心しなさい」ということ
だったんですね
Don’t worry.’
初めて分かりました
I was watching it
on the train on my way to work.
通勤途中の電車で見ていたのですが
I thought, ‘Wow, this is so good!’
これがすごくいいビデオなんです
夢中になって見ていたら
降りるはずの駅を
I was absorbed in the video,
and I missed my train station.
うっかり過ぎてしまいました
So I changed trains, but again,
反対方向の電車に乗り換えたんですが
I was watching the video
and missed my station again!
ビデオを見ていてまたまた
乗り過ごしてしまったんです
The book of Matthew is that interesting.
それほど「マタイ」は楽しいんです
神のかたちに造られている人間にとって
Humans have beneficial feelings
本来持っている有益な感情
というものがあるわけですが
because we are created in God’s image.
残念ながらサタンの体制によって
But because of Satan’s system of things,
these feelings are driven away.
その有益な感情が
奥へ奥へと押しやられています
でも神の言葉を人々に向けたり
However, when you show God’s Word
to people or read it yourself,
私たちも神の言葉を読むと
innate beneficial feelings
well up in our hearts.
その本来持っている有益な
感情が湧き上がってくる
そういう力が神の言葉には
あるんだなっていうことを
I strongly feel that God’s Word
has the power to do that.
強く感じています
Just like a child grows up
listening to what their father says,
子供が父親に話しかけられて育つように
エホバが私の母語で話しかけて
くださるのを見ると
I can be closer to my Father,
Jehovah, by watching him
父としてエホバをもっと身近に感じます
speak to me
in my native tongue, sign language.
Comments from deaf brothers show
手話版の聖書が
ろう者の心に語りかけている
っていうのがよく分かります
that the sign-language Bible
talks to their heart directly.
I imagine that Jehovah loves our brothers,
エホバが本当に兄弟たちのことを
愛しておられて
and his face is shining.
ご自分の顔を輝かせておられる
And the faces of our brothers
are also shining.
そういう様子を思い浮かべる
ことができますし
兄弟たちの顔も本当に光り
輝いているように思います
Now by means of having God’s living Word
心に響く言語で神の生きた言葉を見る時
in the language of their heart,
ろう者の兄弟姉妹は
our deaf brothers and sisters
エホバが向けておられる笑顔を
見ることができるのです
are seeing Jehovah’s face shining.